[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, I've heard that the same thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that's what I mean when I say you don't want to have to do anything on account of suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't want to have to manage it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't want to have to do this when it arises like this, or do that when it arises in a different way.
[SPEAKER_02]: You want to find a place, and that's what dhamma is all about, whereby you can't even suffer in the first place.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you're not just free from any actual suffering, you're free from possibility to experience suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: And Nibbīrā did say similar.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ah, the dhamma doesn't free you from this unpleasant experience or that unpleasant experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: It frees you from the nature of experience altogether.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, again, talking about the impermanence of the stone or the tree or modern science has proven the molecules are changing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Who cares?
[SPEAKER_02]: It's utterly irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can say that, like, you know, the room is like this, the sun is like that, these are the chemicals.
[SPEAKER_02]: It absolutely makes no difference to, like, the existential aspect of your daily life, what you feel.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's another perception.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, it's another perception, it's another view, it's another external explanation.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you have to be honest with yourself and see whereby when there is a suffering and you start using a method to deal with that suffering, be it science, or the suttas, or psychology, or psychotherapy, or any other religion, you have to be honest with yourself to see if that method pertains to management of suffering or to actually uprooting it all together.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you'll find out that dhamma, only dhamma, only correctly practiced, uproots the suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: Everything else is a management, and it's a response to suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: The whole psychotherapy thing, that's big in the West.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just managing the symptoms, not being able to cure yourself from the actual illness.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why I would say, people, it's wrong.
[SPEAKER_02]: You say, well, it helps.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, it helps on a level of contusion, on a mundane level.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you were to know clearly that what you're doing is not the medicine against suffering, it's only managing the symptoms.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you're very, very clear on it, like, you know, when you're taking a drug that can screw you up, so you're very careful, you know, okay, well, they just want this too much, so that I can go and find the proper drug.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, sure, okay, when the mind is weak, there's no, like, right view in sight, people will need that kind of support.
[SPEAKER_02]: But actually, actively practicing, nobody will do it that way.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if you already have that much self-transparency, you'll find that help in the suttas already.
[SPEAKER_02]: You wouldn't need a Western take on, kind of, psychological quasi-medicinal, who knows what, explanation of your mental states.
[SPEAKER_02]: But people don't see that, which is why basically... and the reason why it's wrong is because then they assume that's the practice of dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the same.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is why, like, lots of monks, lots of senior rajas, they go to the psychotherapy workshops and stuff, as if that contributes to their dhamma practice.
[SPEAKER_02]: As if that can contribute to the dhamma practice.
[SPEAKER_02]: It can't.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it just pertains to a completely different thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the worst bit about it is thinking that by doing that, you're doing dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: Means, then, you won't be looking for the right cure, because you think you're having it.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you think that management of your symptoms is the cure, actually, of your illness, you won't be looking for the right cure of your illness, because you're thinking you're curing it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you have to be clear with yourself to recognize whether it's really curing it or is it managing it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, that's what sīla is for.
[SPEAKER_02]: Again, psychotherapy is not needed.
[SPEAKER_02]: Western science is... well, not needed.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's actually a wrong view.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a view that assumes the public world accessible to all of us at the same time, whereby matter is measurable.
[SPEAKER_02]: As Buddha said, matter is always below your feet.
[SPEAKER_02]: Never.
[SPEAKER_02]: It can never appear in your experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: All you're going to have is nāmarūpa, kind of nāma in relation, a designation in relation to the offered resistance.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, things are much more subtle and much more contemplated, complicated, than taking up a ruler or doing, like, you know, some big equation in physics or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's explanatory.
[SPEAKER_02]: It defines the world in its own terms, terms that are developed by science.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why, like, inherently, you can't use science or any other
[SPEAKER_02]: discipline of that kind to explain your experience, because your experience precedes them.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, whether you're a scientist, a philosopher, or whatever, or nothing, you exist.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can then go and develop yourself, concoct scientific explanations, observations, and then use them to explain the tools that you used
[SPEAKER_02]: To recognize those explanations and, in other words, you can't use your senses to access the existence of your senses.
[SPEAKER_02]: Your eye cannot see your eye.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't hear your own ears.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, relying on the measure of the sound to explain your ears, it's a mistake, because it requires your ears beforehand.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can't use it to then, like, explain its roots, because it's a result of it, not a cause of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is why the only way to access these things is
[SPEAKER_02]: Phenomenology.
[SPEAKER_02]: And by that, I don't mean like Western philosophy.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean phenomena, knowledge of phenomena, phenomenology, which is what pertains to the mind, which is what dhamma is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, within your understanding, how would you call what samādhi is?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, I was just reading the Ajahn Chah's quote.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the establishment of the mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: The mind is established properly.
[SPEAKER_02]: And understanding is a form of samādhi.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is why samatha and vipassana, again, preceded by the right view, not without the right view.
[SPEAKER_02]: There is no vipassana and there is no samatha.
[SPEAKER_02]: For somebody who has a right view, samatha and vipassana go hand in hand.
[SPEAKER_02]: Inseparable.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you can't... Because that's one big thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: People think, oh, there is the study and then there is a form of meditation.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: Your study is your meditation, if you do it right.
[SPEAKER_02]: And your meditation is your study, if you do it right.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, sure, there is the aspect of gaining information, gaining knowledge.
[SPEAKER_02]: No doubt about that.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that's just preliminary.
[SPEAKER_02]: What exactly do you mean by establishment of mind?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, like, say, if I try to explain you the solution to a problem, and you understand it, your mind is established upon that understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: You gained that understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, how is it different to, let's say, concentration?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, it's not different, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: It requires concentration.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the concentration is misunderstood to be that which shuts things out, as opposed to that which includes all things in.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's the the other sutta where the Buddha gives a simile of a man who has to keep an eye on, I don't know, fifty children.
[SPEAKER_02]: He can't trace all of them, all the time.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if he goes after one specifically, he loses sight of all the others.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, he has some wisdom, so he recognizes that, and then he finds an elevated place in the yard, where he can climb up, and then from there, see all children, all the time, at once.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which means, ah, he keeps an eye on all of them, by stepping back.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's also from one-pointedness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Usually, people think you focus so hard until all the other children disappear, and then you forget that you are supposed to take care of 29 children more, not just one.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're paying attention to the future, right?
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's why the Buddha said that, like, the foundation of every practice of samādhi is mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Every jhāna is underlined by mindfulness, like, the establishment of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this one has to have... must have the right view in order to attain jhānas?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, not necessarily.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: See, jhānas... the practice of jhāna is along the right view, naturally, in its nature, which is why the Buddha praised it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Theoretically, it's possible to have jhānas without having the right view.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you would have to
[SPEAKER_02]: Never ever hear even a single stanza of Buddhist teaching.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it's it's really so close.
[SPEAKER_02]: So Putujan can get there.
[SPEAKER_02]: And theoretically, let's say somebody does have jhānas.
[SPEAKER_02]: He never had a buddhism.
[SPEAKER_02]: For him, it would probably be enough, depending on how established he is in his jhānas, just one sentence pertaining to the essence of the dhamma, and he'll become an Arya, if not, if not, if not arahant all the way.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which were the cases in the sūtras.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because the mānas were actually established, so all of the pollutions were cleared.
[SPEAKER_02]: They just needed the last tweak, the last kind of drop of dye that will color everything rightly.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, but today, it's quite unlikely that a person would have jhānas and not be a sotāpanna, at least.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, you know, like, again, if you talk about jhānas, means you have come across Buddhist teaching, means you have read.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you are actually developing jhānas, you will be developing your right understanding through that.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why it's, it's, it's often whenever... What's the right meditation?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, first of all, in the Samādhi Sutra, they said that every aspect of the right view is right because of the right view.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sorry, every, every aspect of the Noble Eightfold Path is right because of the right view.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, Samasamādhi is, is right because of Samādhi.
[SPEAKER_02]: Everything is right because of Samādhi.
[SPEAKER_02]: So,
[SPEAKER_02]: Provide the person has the right view, what would be the right meditation for them?
[SPEAKER_02]: Establishing your mind through jhānas.
[SPEAKER_02]: What is a jhāna?
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the establishment of mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if your mind is established to such an extent... How?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, to a certain extent, for different...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's not, again,
[SPEAKER_02]: Famous ānāpānasati sutta, that people teach meditation on breathing, you enter jhāna.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not necessarily.
[SPEAKER_02]: You enter jhāna if you know how to enter jhāna.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you establish your mind in that way, if you know how to establish your mind in that way.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ānāpānasati never mentions jhānas.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ānāpānasati sutta doesn't talk about jhānas, talks about mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Practicing ānāpānasati develops the four foundations of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_02]: The four foundations of mindfulness develop the
[SPEAKER_02]: Four powers.
[SPEAKER_02]: Four powers develop the seven enlightening factors.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or something like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: I might mix it up.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm tired.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that's the point.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's no mention of jhānas.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is enough to undermine the kind of common perception that you automatically enter jhāna through watching your breath.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then I get this experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or something like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: Jhāna is a stem stream of mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: And when the Buddha did talk about it, he listed all sorts of things.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can use it to establish your mind upon, and thus, enter jhāna.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ānāpānasati is just one of them.
[SPEAKER_02]: Staring at a dead body.
[SPEAKER_02]: Staring at decomposed bodies.
[SPEAKER_02]: Practicing ānāpānasati, and then there was... kasiṇas.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can use kasiṇas to establish your mind in jhānas.
[SPEAKER_02]: Eh... air, water, various things.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then also, the suttas, whenever the suttas talk about establishment of mind, there are jhānas, then there are those
[SPEAKER_02]: Immaterial.
[SPEAKER_02]: They refer to them as immaterial jhānas, but they're actually immaterial establishments of mind, of a different kind.
[SPEAKER_02]: Equally wholesome, like neither perception nor perception, and infinite space, infinite consciousness, and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: Again, people assume that's like the extension of the four jhānas, or they're all in the four, or almost whatever.
[SPEAKER_02]: I can't even remember the commentaries of those schemes and divisions.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, all of those are establishments of mind, same like ten casinos.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, that water, fire, air, blue, yellow,
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the Buddha talks about them, I think only one or two suttas, but in the same way.
[SPEAKER_02]: He establishes his mind upon the earth element.
[SPEAKER_02]: He knows the extent of that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, he recognizes that establishment.
[SPEAKER_02]: He's confident.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because of that refined establishment, he abandons everything else that's inferior to that.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if you look what's what's inferior to the element of worth, element of resistance, you realize, well, everything, you know, everything, particularly in your experience, is inferior to the establishment upon element of worth.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, a person can do that.
[SPEAKER_02]: A Tujana can do that.
[SPEAKER_02]: But they wouldn't appraise it, because it's still a great deal of wisdom.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if somebody does that on their own, and then hears the dhamma, they won't... like, it would be easy for them to really understand it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then, he also did refer to it in the same sense as he referred to satyagraha.
[SPEAKER_02]: But some of these people, if they don't make the effort, they don't see that there is beyond.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you don't see the danger, the gratification and the escape in regard to the kāsina, which is usually the same thing you would use for sensuality, the same way, the gratification, the danger of gratification and the escape.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, the target sees that, and then he abandons it because of that, so he goes to establish upon more refined kāsina, more refined kāsina, more...
[SPEAKER_02]: But you can use... you don't have to establish all of them.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can use any of them.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can establish yourself on any of them, and then see this.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's a different way of looking at your establishment.
[SPEAKER_02]: But because establishment is wholesome, when you're established, then you see the danger, the gratification, and the escape in regard to that refined, wholesome establishment of your mind, means
[SPEAKER_02]: You did purify your mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, if you manage to abandon and let go of that refined thing, like, what can be said for all those unwholesome things?
[SPEAKER_02]: They just fall off, never to return.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, he goes and he talks about, like, so, the earth, water, fire, air, about every casino.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then he says, well, some of these people don't see the danger in escape.
[SPEAKER_02]: Tathāgata does.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which means seeing danger in escape.
[SPEAKER_02]: Danger, gratification and escape in regard to any particular kasiṇa is the development of wisdom, which is a different thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then, it wouldn't be there if you didn't establish your mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, through the establishment of mind, you can see things particularly, and then be completely free, regardless of whether your mind continues to be established or not, which is what arahanthip is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, he goes to say about the Consciousness Casino, like, the most refined casino of all, and everybody, every Simon and Brown, they agree on that.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, so, somebody might establish the mind upon that.
[SPEAKER_02]: They abandon not just all of the inferior, they abandon all the other casinos, because they establish upon the ultimate refinement of the mind, and says... And then, the target sees the danger, the gratification, and the escape in regard to that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the basis for wisdom should... is basically the establishment of mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: If there is no basis for wisdom, the mind is not established properly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sometimes you can have mind established properly, but then you don't know what to look for, so you don't pursue that as basis for your wisdom.
[SPEAKER_02]: In that way, it's like samādhi is necessary.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't not have a degree of your mind establishment and expect wisdom to arise.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then, you cannot have a right view and, like, correct instructions and expect the wisdom to arise, because you won't be... you wouldn't know what to look for.
[SPEAKER_02]: You wouldn't know how to recognize danger, you wouldn't know how to discern gratification, and you wouldn't know what escape is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not knowing those things means the wisdom lacks development.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, first jhāna can be basis for that, second jhāna can be basis for that, any jhāna can be basis for that, any kāsina can be...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, there are certain right meditations in themselves, but none of them is actually right, if there is no right view enabling them to act as basis for your wisdom.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the Buddha said that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Without the right view, jhāna is just pleasant abiding here and now.
[SPEAKER_02]: Nothing more.
[SPEAKER_02]: But he's developing wisdom in regard to that, that it's called, eh... effacement, wasn't it?
[SPEAKER_02]: It was the effacement sutra.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, concentration is one of the characteristics of establishment of mind?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, right concentration, again, will be right only with the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what... the right view arises through two factors.
[SPEAKER_01]: The word of another and...
[SPEAKER_01]: Proper attention.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the thing, you've got to know what proper attention is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, so, and proper attention is...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a form of samādhi.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, knowing how to establish your mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why, for the right view, you like, you don't need jhānas or something, but you need a citta, nimitta.
[SPEAKER_02]: You need to have grasped the sign, nimitta, of your mind, like the phenomenological appearance of your mind, which is there as a phenomenon, ambiguous.
[SPEAKER_02]: Most people don't see it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because they're only used to... they only qualify as real what they experience through their senses.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's real, everything else is not real.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, when they deny their own thoughts as real things, how far removed they are from seeing that, like, the subtle shape of your mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: The expanded mind, he knows, is the expanded mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't go in more detail, because it's not more detailed.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the detail it has.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's aloof.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's depressed.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's contracted.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's expanded.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's elated.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not.
[SPEAKER_02]: The general mood, well, like recognizing your mind on those terms, on those ambiguous terms, means grasping the signs that your mind shows you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, the side of the mind means the way it has appeared.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like a sign.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, ah, you see the contours of something.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ah, you're grasping the signs of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well...
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, I mean, in a sense, it just really depends how we... how we choose to use the words, because... You don't recognize.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you have no choice but to have your mind there.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's not that through not seeing their mind, the mind is not there.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's there.
[SPEAKER_02]: They just don't have a clue.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ignorant.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, are you seeing in terms of knowing it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, oh, they see their mind, means they know their mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: They recognize their mind as such.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, would I be wrong, or rather, um, would it be wrong to use the word focus to describe stagnation?
[SPEAKER_02]: You probably would.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because focus takes people out.
[SPEAKER_02]: You get focused on something.
[SPEAKER_02]: Uh, what you should do, get focused on something, and then start looking at yourself being focused on something.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's a proper development of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Focus yourself on something, if you want, but then develop notions of tokens, pick up the tokens of the phenomena of you being focused upon something, right there.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you get focused on something, and then you see yourself being focused on something.
[SPEAKER_02]: And?
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the beginning.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a recognition.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, that can lead to recognition.
[SPEAKER_02]: Basically, you need to recognize the principle of, like, well, like peripheral vision.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you look at things directly, well, you don't see what's peripheral to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you have to learn how to, which is what proper attention is, how to be able to start noticing things peripherally, or more generally, without over-intending them, without making them into actual direct.
[SPEAKER_02]: which removes the nature of peripheral, which means something else is non-peripheral, and you're not seeing it as an established phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because there is a domain of the left, focused, actual, in front of you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Simultaneous to that, there's a domain of peripheral, negative, background, general, ambiguous.
[SPEAKER_02]: And they both exist.
[SPEAKER_02]: They're both real, as such, in their own domains, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, for as long as you're using
[SPEAKER_02]: The tools, the assumptions of... based upon actual and direct, you'll never be able to access peripheral in its... on its own terms, in its own domain, which means you're not actually peripheral.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're just thinking about actual and then developing views about that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, any... that's why the question of science, anything, exact sciences, which all require focus, external measure, they're basically, well, self-defeating when it comes to practicing the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because they cannot, in their nature, pertain
[SPEAKER_02]: Can we start off with being focused?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, as long as you know that that's just one aspect of your experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the thing is, if you see yourself being focused, if you know where you're supposed to look, that the moment you see yourself doing anything, that will be a form of focus.
[SPEAKER_02]: So you don't have to be specifically focused on yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: You have to establish sīla, so there is no unwholesome focus of any kind.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, upon whatever you focus at the time, you can see yourself being focused on that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because that's the point.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's how to develop mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not by choosing a magical focus or finding a magical object of your focus.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, in that sense, you should really make your effort to find out how to get established in that peripheral vision, because that will make you focused, actually, directly, upon whatever... whatever is present.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which also means, your focus of any kind will not be dependent upon anything external, but it will be dependent upon your mindfulness, for which you're fully responsible, which means you're in control of your own focus.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whatever your mind... you're in control of whatever your mind goes, through that mindfulness, through having that basis of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so, going back to that example you came up with earlier.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you look after the fifty children, but you're not trying to connect to the fifty children.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, why would you?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, that's not looking after, exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because while you were connecting, means you're losing sight of the others, because you can't connect all of them at once.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's like recognizing the important from unimportant.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, no, the point is to keep an eye on that, focus on that, you keep an eye on that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can also keep an eye on all of them.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's kind of extending the simile, but no, the simile just refers to the actual practice of samādhi, which you can see it's completely founded upon mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, rather than thinking in concentration and focus, if you want to think about the samādhi, even in Plutonian terms, you should think in terms of unwavering mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_02]: When you're so mindful that you are not unmindful, means you're established in samādhi.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then you say, oh, okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what is... then you say you have to actually make the effort to realize, to understand what mindfulness is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: And through understanding mindfulness, then you will develop that mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not like one thing that... No.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's through that understanding, you will develop mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_02]: You will be mindful.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's how the whole dhamma works.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, if you were to understand what arahantship is, you'd be on your way to become an arahant, if not the arahant.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can't entertain the notions of thinking you know what arahantship is and what dhamma is and meditation is, and at the same time know that you're a putrīcchana.
[SPEAKER_01]: I remember, eh, when I was practicing, I liked to do general awareness.
[SPEAKER_01]: I was working in a shop and I was doing this general awareness.
[SPEAKER_01]: I was trying to be mindful.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, eh, as I was doing that... You lost the sight of what's going on in front of you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's good.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: It means you're so concerned about keeping around 50 children, you start thinking about 50 children and then lost sight of them.
[SPEAKER_02]: They were right in front of you.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can't have it disconnected from whatever... which is why, like, the Buddha refers to mindfulness of the body and bodily postures.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because that's always the anchor right there in the actual test of your senses, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's always in relation to that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, yeah, oh, fifty children.
[SPEAKER_02]: What if I lose them?
[SPEAKER_02]: What if I... and by getting caught up in thinking like that, and being really concerned not to lose them, you know, you stop noticing them.
[SPEAKER_01]: They run off.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you've got body posture, general awareness... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not just focused on the body posture, solely on that, or focused solely on general awareness, but having both those, eh... that is where you've... that is the anicca, that is the...
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the akālaka, it's the principle of simultaneity, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't... so you can't find it when you're focused on something, looking at a stone, or looking at a breath, seeing that disappear, because that's not the anicca, is it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: You want to see that... Yeah, anicca is undermining.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, the impermanence that undermines whatever you're established upon.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's exactly that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Say, general awareness in the present body.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you wouldn't be generally aware if your body is not alive there, if your organs are not still operating.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's really undermines in this side of the ship.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, if you take your... nāmarūpa, viññāṇa, viññāṇa, nāmarūpa, mutually determining itself, each other.
[SPEAKER_02]: So,
[SPEAKER_02]: If you're taking up nāma-rūpa, you undermine that permanence by seeing it dependent simultaneously while you are still holding it, up on viññāṇa.
[SPEAKER_02]: If taking viññāṇa, you see it's simultaneously dependent upon nāma-rūpa.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's either-or.
[SPEAKER_02]: There is no in-between, or left or right, where you can step aside and then look at both.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, either this is determined by nāma-rūpa, viññāṇa, or it's viññāṇa determining nāma-rūpa.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's your experience, always.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why not the other?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, by recognizing this general, in the particular actual body, you will be start, like, not knowingly in the beginning, but you will be ambit in those principles.
[SPEAKER_02]: And actually, you can even continue the reflection, as I just started saying, you wouldn't be aware of anything, no matter how general or particular, if your body is not alive here.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like the organs that you have no control over, your heart, your eyes, they're not there functioning.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just your awareness will be inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_02]: You won't be able to think.
[SPEAKER_02]: At the same time, if there is no thinking of any kind, you wouldn't know those organs as organs.
[SPEAKER_02]: You wouldn't know anything as anything.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_02]: Things without a name are inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's nāmarūpa.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you can't have just rūpa, pure rūpa.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: You only can have nāma of the rūpa.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nāma is...
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you could say it's the all that appears, basically.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the reason why it appears is because consciousness is out there with the rūpa.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that's a different topic.
[SPEAKER_02]: The point is, you can see your day-to-day mindfulness is fully dependent upon, like, random organs of your living body operating in their function, that you cannot control.
[SPEAKER_02]: If that changes, you're dead.
[SPEAKER_02]: And they will change.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, at the same time, you are mindful, generally, and you're mindful of the very, like, undermining foundations of your own existence.
[SPEAKER_02]: You realize, well, whatever I do, mindfully or unmindfully, aware or unaware, it's fully determined by these random organs they have no control over.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then you might start thinking about the random organs as more fundamental, but then you realize, well, that's just my thought of that which a random organ is.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's your name.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which means random organ would be inconceivable if there is not even a degree of awareness in regard to that.
[SPEAKER_02]: If the name of an organ doesn't appear.
[SPEAKER_02]: If it doesn't appear in experience as anything.
[SPEAKER_02]: If something doesn't appear, you can't even conceive it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You suddenly can't talk about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's enough to show you that, well, these random organs operate, but they wouldn't be operating if there is no consciousness in regard to them, if there is no awareness in regard to them.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I mean by that, even the living heart would not be living heart if there is no consciousness associated with the body as a unit.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, in that sense, you start recognizing the consciousness is on the level of those random organs outside.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, below the threshold that you can see or perceive through any sense, it's the foundation of your senses.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's not in your head, or inside of you, or on this side, and then rūpa is on that side.
[SPEAKER_02]: The rūpa and viññāṇa are there, and the kind of result of that is nāma, rūpa, viññāṇa.
[SPEAKER_02]: Your experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, your experience, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that's what I meant before when I said, well, whatever you think is your thought, or presentation.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or phenomena, or dhamma, whatever you want to translate it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's all you can ever have in regard to different things.
[SPEAKER_02]: But even when you say different things, that's another thought.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can never step outside of your mind and say, this is the real thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: That the real thing is known only because your mind knows it as such.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the priority of the mind, the first... the first verse of... of dhammapāda.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mind is the forerunner of all things.
[SPEAKER_02]: Structural forerunner.
[SPEAKER_02]: It would be inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, when you talk about rūpa, or any other aggregate, you're talking through your mind, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_02]: In other words, you have to know that when you say rūpa, when you say this, when you say that, that cannot stand for the actual elements.
[SPEAKER_02]: Assuming that it does stand, means you conceive those elements in your thoughts.
[SPEAKER_02]: Your thoughts are conceiving, and that's exactly mūḍha-pariyāya-sūtra.
[SPEAKER_02]: Assuming the discrepancy of any kind, means you give them existence in your thoughts.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, like, you know, the five codes of mastering your thoughts, and one who masters his thoughts all together, he's an arahant.
[SPEAKER_02]: The danger there is, when you say thoughts, people think abstract, kind of theoretical, proliferating.
[SPEAKER_02]: But no.
[SPEAKER_02]: Looking at the door is a thought experience as well.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, another danger is becoming a... like falling into solipsism and thinking, oh, it's all in my head.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, a thought that things are in your head is another thought that is present, and that cannot be in your head.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, a thought in my head, the space, this, opposite, that's all, again,
[SPEAKER_02]: A phenomenon that has arisen on the level of the mind, which is where things arise.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, within that, you can distinguish different types of phenomena, but they all have things in common, which is, they share the same nature of appearing, manifesting.
[SPEAKER_02]: And on that level, they're all phenomena, they're all phenomenological, which is why they're all dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, all of the aggregates are dhammas.
[SPEAKER_02]: And saṅkharas.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not at the same time, obviously, but
[SPEAKER_02]: They serve as that which determines and that which is determined, depending on where your attention is.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't step outside of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why I said nāmarūpa, viññāṇa, nāmarūpa.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's always either or.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, every experience is...
[SPEAKER_02]: Either nāmarūpa, viññāṇa, either two of them being combined or three of them... No, every experience, no, no, no, every experience, depending again on the approach, but in this sense, every experience is either founded upon nāmarūpa or either founded upon viññāṇa.
[SPEAKER_02]: And by that I mean determined by.
[SPEAKER_02]: As far as... You can't have nāmarūpa and viññāṇa equally in front of you.
[SPEAKER_02]: You will be one of them.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which means the other one can be, if seen correctly, can be the, the, the... Yeah, the undermining factor that will remove your sense of self.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you see that my sense of self depends upon that which, right now, while I'm holding this, while this is me, depends fully upon that which is not me.
[SPEAKER_02]: And actually, I just gave you the example, a rather general one, but it's a good start.
[SPEAKER_02]: Your organs, your bodily organs.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you have to bring down, you have to recognize the connection between the presence of a random working heart and your entire life.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, literally, working heart is like, like, like an object out there in the world.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's an object because of which the objects exist as phenomena.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's a particular type of object that enables your experience as such, because it's paired with consciousness, matter in consciousness, but none of which you can actually access or have an in.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, control or input open.
[SPEAKER_02]: They're utterly beyond, outside of your reach.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, all you're going to have is a presentation, or their appearance, in a way.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can know the direction they appeared from, but you can't, like, hold them.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't get... because if you would, arhanty would not be possible.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if the... if the... if the fundamentals, if the foundations of your experience would genuinely be within your reach, you would... there would be a self, there would be a creator, there would be at least somebody you can take the ownership of.
[SPEAKER_02]: But there aren't, which is why, like... which is why the sense of self, or a vijja, or whatever else, it's completely unnecessary.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a parasite, is the only way to refer to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not, it's just... it can't be there, but not knowing that it can't be there, it's there.
[SPEAKER_02]: There is no room for a vijja in the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not knowing that there is no room for a vijja, not fully understanding what that means,
[SPEAKER_02]: You make the rūpa.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, it's not like... it's not exactly an easy matter, but...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the good... the good way to start is, when you... when you take up a contemplation, you read the Sutta and the Five Agreements and be conscious of yourself, instead of trying to figure out what it all is, start by undoing what you think it all is.
[SPEAKER_02]: In other words, nobody talks about nāra, or nā, or say nāmarūpa, viññāṇa, nāmarūpa.
[SPEAKER_02]: They say, okay, it's nāmarūpa.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, before you can understand that, first, you have to purify what nāmarūpa designation stands for in your experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: What consciousness stands for in your experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you were to take up five aggregates and name them, in English, or Sinhala, or whatever, just repeat the name two or three times.
[SPEAKER_02]: Do you know, at that time,
[SPEAKER_02]: What that matter stands for in your experience, when you say, ah, matter, and see directly what that matter is.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you realize you don't.
[SPEAKER_02]: You take all of them and you realize you do use them, you do have some general notion of what they are, what they pretend to, but you don't actually understand what they are.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you realize the practice is completely the opposite direction you've been aiming at.
[SPEAKER_02]: See, I'm trying to figure it all out.
[SPEAKER_02]: You have to undo it, to the extent necessary, when the recognition of what they are takes place, based on the external instruction laid down by the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, that's right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Actually, a lot of dharma is based on stuff like
[SPEAKER_00]: You say five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: I try to reach the five aggregates and I'm lost.
[SPEAKER_00]: So now I'm trying to, you know, get them back.
[SPEAKER_02]: So you take them, you can't change their order, so take them as they are, rūpa, vedanā, sañña, saṅkhāra, viññāṇa, and literally just a matter and then ponder.
[SPEAKER_02]: What is that matter?
[SPEAKER_02]: How would you describe it, even in your own terms?
[SPEAKER_02]: Do you see that which matter is, in your experience, when you make utter designation matter?
[SPEAKER_02]: Same for the feeling, same for the perception, same for the intention, same for the consciousness.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you keep drilling inwards, as opposed to building up outwards.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, you have to make it clean, accurate, in a sense whereby, when you read the sutta, when you read the five aggregates, you immediately see what there is in your experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't have to stop and think about it and bring... evoke the memory of what you thought once, which is why... how people became arahants just by listening to the Buddha once.
[SPEAKER_02]: They knew exactly what he was talking about.
[SPEAKER_02]: They didn't know the dhamma, but they knew, when he was speaking, what he was referring to, at the time.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, by seeing those things, they are at the arahantship, at the full understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the reason why we don't become arahants now, when you read the sutra, is because the terms that you read, you hold completely wrongly.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, they don't actually pertain to that which they actually are.
[SPEAKER_02]: If there would, you would arrive at understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: Inevitably.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why, like, correctly practicing dhamma has to result in... well, has to have the result.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't be correctly practicing and not arriving anywhere.
[SPEAKER_02]: It just doesn't work.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if somebody tells you, I've been practicing dhamma 40 years, but it's not about becoming Sotāpanna and stuff, you turn away that moment and don't listen to what they say.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, actually, if somebody's been practicing for 40, 50, 60 years, and not even get the right view, it means they've been wasting their time for 60 years.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, rather than presenting that as some sort of skill, as some sort of great achievement, you should be embarrassed.
[SPEAKER_02]: And Ajahn Chah said the same.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you're not solved the problem in the first five years, it means you're wasting your time.
[SPEAKER_02]: And people are not, because they misdirect their efforts, or they don't have enough effort, or they don't bother in the first place, or whatever.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, again, it all comes down, comes back to that self-transparency, like knowing for yourself, having that as a goal.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's a reason the Buddha laid it down, explained it, and encouraged monks to contemplate.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you were to understand what sotāpati is, you'll be a sotāpati.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you were to understand what freedom from three first factors is, you'll be free from the three first factors.
[SPEAKER_02]: There is no, like, discrepancy between understanding and then actually the reality of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: Understanding is the reality of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Obviously, it needs to be developed to the extent necessary, and then it gets fully understood.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, you can't separate five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't separate them.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't change their order.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can individually do it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can, you can individually be reviewing your designations of what you assume the five aggregates are.
[SPEAKER_02]: But even that should be done in the order.
[SPEAKER_02]: You start with the method.
[SPEAKER_02]: And feeling in regard to that method, and perception in regard to the method, and your intentions in regard to the method.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, that which you think consciousness is, you guys will admit it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Eric, in regards to admittance, you don't lose the sight of that?
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't lose the sight, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's how you keep the order.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's how you affect them all.
[SPEAKER_02]: Try a contemplation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Understanding consciousness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if you were to just take up Consciousness randomly, it means, oh, you're just assuming it now.
[SPEAKER_02]: Again, through your own assumption, the Consciousness can stand randomly, independent of anything else.
[SPEAKER_02]: It can't.
[SPEAKER_02]: None of them can, which is why it's always the five heaps, the five aggari.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not, not, not two and three.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can single out one of them while all of them are present.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, on the basis of all of them, you can attend one or the other more particularly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're usually taking one of them.
[SPEAKER_02]: One of them or all of them?
[SPEAKER_02]: One of them.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's another thing you should start thinking.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, when you say five aggregates, it's not somewhere else.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I think, right now, I will speak your experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what five aggregates are.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, instead of trying to, like, think about what they might be, you start looking.
[SPEAKER_02]: In the general experience that you're mindful of right now, and discerning within that, because they're there.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you forget that they're right here, right now, and go looking for them, even if you find something, that something will not be there because of which you started looking in the first place, because it was right there.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's what I mean, like, you start reviewing, you start basically learning how to discern, because you know, you were told, you have faith enough, that your experience as a whole, actual and peripheral, whatever else, whatever other approach you take, it's present right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_02]: All, like, all of them.
[SPEAKER_02]: Your experience is the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_02]: Any experience you had, any experience you have, will be the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the Buddha said that when somebody recalls five lifetimes or five hundred lifetimes, what they'll recall is these five aggregates or one specifically unknown thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's all within that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So you start training yourself how to discern them within this mindful picture that you established for.
[SPEAKER_00]: Matter is nāmarūpa.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sorry?